A Guide to the Nelson A. Rockefeller personal papers, Speeches, Post-Vice Presidential, Series M FA349
Rockefeller Archive Center
Nelson A. Rockefeller personal papers, Speeches, Post-Vice Presidential, Series M
1977-1979
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller, Nelson A. (Nelson Aldrich) (1908-1979)
Morrow, Hugh
FA349
1.88 Cubic Feet 4 legal document boxes.
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Material in the Rockefeller family collections that provides the names, correspondence, or activities of living members of the Rockefeller family, and/or documents the net wealth of any Rockefeller family members, is restricted. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) or audiovisual material (audio cassettes, VHS, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Arrangement note
The series is arranged chronologically by date of the speech.
Scope and Contents note
This speech file was maintained by Hugh Morrow, Nelson Rockefeller's press secretary. Mr. Morrow was a speech writer for Mr. Rockefeller during his first term as Governor of New York and became his press secretary beginning with his second term in 1963. Mr. Morrow served Mr. Rockefeller throughout his term as Vice President and during his years as a private citizen before and after the Vice Presidency.
This collection of speeches and press releases reflects Rockefeller's transition from public official to a private citizen and offers some insight to his public activities during the last two years of his life. Mr. Rockefeller maintained his reputation as a knowledgeable and outspoken observer of politics and foreign affairs by accepting invitations to speak before political, civic, and private groups. He addressed issues such as the energy crisis, Soviet expansion, national security, and peace in the Middle East. After returning to private life, Mr. Rockefeller also indulged his passion for art by establishing two related businesses: an art reproduction company called the Nelson Rockefeller Collection, Inc. (NRC) and an art book publishing business called Nelson Rockefeller Publications, Inc. This series includes press releases announcing the establishment and development of these two ventures. At Mr. Morrow's suggestion, Nelson Rockefeller began to cultivate a public image as an art dealer and art expert by accepting invitations to give lectures on art. Transcripts for two such lectures, on December 16, 1977, and November 15, 1978, are included. There is also a tape recording of the first one.
This series begins with files of some public remarks Mr. Rockefeller made during the last days of the Ford Administration in January 1977 and concludes with press releases on the memorial services after Rockefeller's death on January 26, 1979. The speech files contain one or more of four different versions of each speech: draft, reading copy, transcript, or press release. The folder descriptions list which versions exist for each speech. Drafts and reading copies are likely to include Mr. Rockefeller's handwritten changes and notations. A transcript is a verbatim record of the remarks. For each speech, Mr. Morrow's office usually issued a press release containing excerpts of Mr. Rockefeller's remarks. Some files contain correspondence, schedules, or background information on the event as well.
Public health -- Latin America; Social problems -- Latin America; Philanthropy -- New York (N.Y.); State governments -- United States; United States; Political campaigns -- United States; Political science; Presidential campaigns -- United States; Presidential candidates -- United States -- History -- 20th century; Philanthropy -- United States; Education; National security -- United States; New York (N.Y.); New York (State); Developing countries; Civics; Economics; Economic policy; Business; Philanthropy -- New York (State); Brazil; Civic improvement; Philanthropy; Business enterprises, Foreign; Agriculture -- Latin America; Agriculture; Arts; Art, Primitive; Government agencies; Government policy; Education -- Latin America; Federal government -- United States; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1962; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1958; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1970; Governors -- Election -- New York (State) -- 1966; International relations; International economic relations; Latin America; International relations -- United States; Venezuela
- 1977 January 5 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Washington, D.C. The Senate. NAR's farewell address to the Senate. Draft, reading copy.
- 1977 January 5 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Washington, D.C. 1912 F Street Club. Humorous address by NAR to members of the cabinet at a cabinet dinner. Drafts.
- 1977 January 12-13 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  January 12, 1977 -- Washington, D.C. The East Room of the White House, Remarks by NAR on behalf of President Gerald R. Ford at the President's Awards for Distinguished Civil Service. Press release. January 13, 1977 -- Press release announcing staff changes in the Vice President's Press Office.
- 1977 January 18 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Transcript of an interview by Dan Rather with Mr. and Mrs. NAR for CBS-TV program, "Who's Who."
- 1977 January 29 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Washington, D.C. The Alfalfa Club. Politically humorous speech. Drafts, correspondence and memoranda.
- 1977 March 16 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  University of California, Davis. Dedication of the Fannie and John Hertz Hall at Lawrence Livermore Laboratory. NAR spoke at the invitation of Edward Teller. NAR speech regarding contribution of applied science to the economy and security of the U.S. Drafts, reading copy, press release, memoranda, correspondence, program and schedule.
- 1977 March 18-30 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Trip to the Middle East to promote NAR's Saudi Arabian and American Investment Co. (SARABAM) to facilitate the investment of Saudi Arabian capital reserves. Schedules for Mr. and Mrs. NAR, suggested statements to be made by NAR at various locations, newspaper clipping regarding the trip.
- 1977 April 12 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Washington, D.C. Carleton Hotel. Federal City Club's Annual Award for Distinguished Public Service given to NAR. Drafts, reading copy.
- 1977 May 9 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  New York City. Waldorf-Astoria Hotel. NAR received the first World Covenant of Peace Award by the Synagogue Council of America. NAR speech on peace in Mideast and other foreign policy issues. Drafts, reading copy, press release, newspaper clippings.
- 1977 June 2 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  New York City. Americana Hotel. Alfred P. Sloan Memorial Dinner honoring Betty Ford and Benno Schmidt. Mr. and Mrs. NAR were dinner chairmen. NAR's schedule for June 2. List of people seated on dais. No NAR remarks.
- 1977 June 16 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  New York City. Waldorf-Astoria Hotel. Republican State Committee Dinner. NAR's speech thanking New York State Republican Party and honoring Former President Gerald R. Ford. Drafts, reading copy, press release, NAR's schedule for June 16, letter by NAR saying thanks and farewell to be included in dinner program.
- 1977 August 30 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Statement by NAR in response to "New York Magazine" article suggesting that he covered up CIA activities while he was Chairman of the Commission on CIA Activities Within the United States. Copy of article and a similar one from the "New York Post." Press release.
- 1977 September 13 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  Washington, D.C. Senate Finance Committee. Statement by NAR on energy crisis and the need for the Energy Development Corporation. Draft, reading copy, press release.
- 1977 October 2 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  Pocantico Hills, New York. Guest list and list of nations represented at a reception for United Nations delegates and friends hosted by Mr. and Mrs. NAR. No recorded NAR remarks.
- 1977 October 14 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  Teheran, Iran. NAR's statement at a reception at the New Museum of Contemporary Arts. Press release.
- 1977 October 26 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  Albany, New York. NAR received honorary doctorate from the University of the State of New York at the Bicentennial Convocation of the Board of Regents. Program of events, correspondence. No recorded NAR remarks.
- 1977 December 16 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  Purchase, New York. Meeting of the Westchester Arts Council. NAR was given the WAC's annual award for distinguished service to the arts and then presented a slide show on art. Transcript of NAR's slide show, memoranda, correspondence, and clippings.
  Moving Images; Sound recordings
  - NAR Art Speech - Complete Audio, 1977 December 16; ¼ inch audio tape; Sound, 77 minutes (Reel AV 9999)
    Conditions Governing Access
    Access copy available.
    Scope and Contents
    Complete audio recording of the SUNY-Purchase event, including speeches and introductions.
  - NAR Art Speech - Slide Presentation, 1977 December 16; Sound, Color, 29 minutes (Reel AV 9999A)
    Video combining slides of artworks with Nelson Rockefeller's art speech at State University of New York College at Purchase. Note: These are not the actual slides used by NAR for hi spresentation, but rather are images of the art works he is discussing.
    Related Materials
    Complete audio from event - AV 9999.
- 1978 March (Box 2, Folder 18)
  Statement by NAR announcing the formation of The Nelson Rockefeller Collection, Inc., an art reproduction company. Press release.
- 1978 March 13 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  Statement by NAR denying suggestions in "Newsweek" that he asked CIA director William Colby to 'stonewall' the Commission on CIA Activities Within the United States, chaired by NAR. Press release.
- 1978 March 28 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  Statement by NAR to the "Daily News" on his interest in recirculating excess oil monies into productive enterprise. Press release.
- 1978 April 14 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  New York City. Aspen Institute for Humanistic Studies' Statesman-Humanist Award given to Dr. Alberto Lleras Camargo. NAR in attendance. Clippings and photocopies of photos. No recorded NAR remarks.
- 1978 May 8 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  Kansas City, Missouri. Harry S. Truman Good Neighbor Award Foundation's Good Neighbor Award presented to NAR at a luncheon. Significant speech on energy and national security. Drafts, reading copy, press release of excerpts, memoranda, correspondence, clippings, schedule of events.
- 1978 May 25 (Box 3, Folder 23)
  U.S. House of Representatives gives Distinguished Service Award to NAR. Remarks by NAR. Drafts, reading copy, press release, schedule of events, copy of "Congressional Record" recording the presentation of the award.
- 1978 May 26 (Box 3, Folder 24)
  NAR statement and memo answering "tax fraud" stories regarding the sale of his Venezuelan ranches to NAR Farms, Inc., in 1958. Press release.
- 1978 May 27 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  Pocantico Hills, New York. NAR's 70th birthday party. Guest list, drafts of unattributed remarks honoring NAR, correspondence regarding press coverage, clippings. No recorded NAR remarks.
- 1978 June 5 (Box 3, Folder 26)
  Albany, New York. Dedication of State University Plaza. Schedule of events. No recorded NAR remarks. Essay on the plaza sent to Hugh Morrow. Clippings of events.
- 1978 June 8 (Box 3, Folder 27)
  New York City. Waldorf Astoria Hotel. National Energy Foundation, Energy Achievement Awards Dinner. NAR was guest speaker. Drafts, reading copy, press release, NEF literature used in preparing speech.
- 1978 July 13 (Box 3, Folder 28)
  New York City. Riverside Church. Memorial Service for John D. Rockefeller 3rd, who died in an automobile accident July 10. Transcript of eulogy by John D. "Jay" Rockefeller IV. Biographical sketch of JDR 3rd, program for service.
- 1978 July 25 (Box 3, Folder 29)
  New York City. Transcript of press conference regarding NAR's arrangement to pay royalties to artists for the right to reproduce certain works of art in his collection. Letters to reporters asking them to attend.
- 1978 August 25 (Box 3, Folder 30)
  Saratoga, New York. NAR attended Saratoga Performing Arts Center for a concert honoring him and in celebration of his birthday. Clippings of event. Correspondence with NAR's office regarding his attending. No recorded NAR remarks.
- 1978 September 7 (Box 3, Folder 31)
  Statement on the mailing of The Nelson Rockefeller Collection, Inc. mail-order catalogs featuring reproductions of works in NAR's private collection. Press release.
- 1978 September 20 (Box 3, Folder 32)
  Hamburg, Germany. Meeting of the Atlantic Treaty Association. NAR was keynote speaker. NAR speech on NATO and Soviet expansion. Draft, reading copy, press release, memoranda, clippings, copy of "Congressional Record" wherein NAR's remarks were accepted into the record of the proceedings of the Senate. List of members of Congress who were sent a copy of the speech.
- 1978 September 25 (Box 3, Folder 33)
  Press release announcing the formation of Nelson Rockefeller Publications, Inc., a company which will produce art books. Photo of Paul Anbinder, Lee Boltin and NAR which was issued with a press release.
- 1978 October 3 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  New York City. Meeting of the International Advisory Board of Pan American World Airways. NAR speech on maintaining perspective in international affairs. Draft, reading copy, press release.
- 1978 October 3 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  New York City. NAR was Chairman of the New York City Mission Society's Capital Campaign. Taping of NAR's narration of Mission Society promotional slide show. Draft, reading copy.
- 1978 October 6 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  Albany, New York. Dedication ceremonies for the newly renamed "Governor Nelson A. Rockefeller Empire State Plaza," formerly the South Mall. Draft, press conference transcript. Remarks by Governor Hugh Carey, program of events, clippings, story of why the Plaza cam to be built.
- 1978 October 26 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  New York City. Waldorf-Astoria Hotel. Meeting of the Rotary Area Assembly. NAR was guest speaker. Speech on John D. Rockefeller, Jr.'s credo. Transcript, program, NAR's schedule for October 26.
- 1978 November 15 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  New York City. Speech on art delivered at the University Club. Transcript, memoranda, correspondence.
- 1979 January 17 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  New York City. Announcement concerning a new reproduction method for The Nelson Rockefeller Collection, Inc. Press release of remarks. Transcript of remarks. List of reporters attending.
- 1979 January 26 (Box 4, Folder 40)
  New York City. The Buckley School. NAR's remarks and introduction of Henry Kissinger to students (including his sons, Nelson, Jr., and Mark). This was NAR's last public appearance. Transcript.
- 1979 January 27 (Box 4, Folder 41)
  New York City. Waldorf-Astoria Hotel. World Antiques Market Conference. NAR was scheduled to attend the conference. Conference literature, press release of NAR's informal remarks which was issued on January 26, memoranda, correspondence concerning NAR's appearance at the conference.
- 1979 January 27 (Box 4, Folder 42)
  New York City. Press release announcing the decision to make a Manhattan retail store a permanent feature of The Nelson Rockefeller Collection, Inc. List of reporters who were sent the release on January 26.
- 1979 January 27 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  New York City. Press releases concerning the private interment service for NAR in Pocantico on January 29 and the public memorial service at Riverside Church on February 2. Statement by Hugh Morrow concerning the place of NAR's death. Memo to 5600 staff stating offices will be closed on February 2 for the memorial service. Lists of dignitaries attending memorial service. Press information sheets about the memorial service.
- 1979 January 27 (Box 4, Folder 44)
  New York City. Statement issued by Laurance Rockefeller on his brother's death.
- 1979 January 29 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  Pocantico. Interment services for NAR. Remarks by Nelson A. Rockefeller, Jr., NAR's son.
- 1979 January 29 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  Pocantico. Interment services for NAR. Remarks by Meile Rockefeller, NAR's granddaughter.
- 1979 February 2 (Box 4, Folder 47)
  New York City. Riverside Church. Memorial Service for NAR. Program for service. List of ushers.
- 1979 February 2 (Box 4, Folder 48)
  New York City. Riverside Church. Memorial Service for NAR. Remarks by Ann Rockefeller Roberts, NAR's elder daughter.
- 1979 February 2 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  New York City. Riverside Church. Memorial Service for NAR. Remarks by Rodman Rockefeller, NAR's eldest son.
- 1979 February 2 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  New York City. Riverside Church. Memorial Service for NAR. Remarks by David Rockefeller, NAR's youngest brother.
- 1979 February 2 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  New York City. Riverside Church. Memorial Service for NAR. Eulogy of NAR delivered by Henry Kissinger.
- 1979 February 9 (Box 4, Folder 52)
  New York City. Press releases and memoranda concerning NAR's will.